Gluyas Williams Papers
Gluyas Williams Papers
1918-1950
Williams, Gluyas, 1888-1982.
1.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American cartoonist, illustrator. Original book illustrations for books by Robert Benchley, Edward Streeter, William Freeman, and Corey Ford, magazine cartoons for Cosmopolitan, Life and The New Yorker, and newspaper cartoons (1922-1947); correspondence, 1918-1949, and manuscript of a poem about Williams by Kenneth Bird and prefaces to Fellow Citizens (1941) and The Gluyas Williams Book, both by Robert Benchley (1929). Correspondents include Randolph G. Adams, Robert Benchley, Kenneth Bird, Charles Dana Gibson, G.S. Lobrano, Christopher Morley, D. Nassau, H.W. Ross, Frank Sullivan, and K.S. White.
148758
Biographical History
Gluyas Williams (1888-1982) was an American cartoonist. Born in San Francisco, California, he received his A.B. from Harvard University in 1911 and, in 1915, married Margaret Kempton.
Mr. William's drawings include book illustrations, magazine cartoons and daily newspaper cartoons. He has illustrated many of Robert Benchley's books, William Freeman's Hear! Hear!, Corey Ford's How to Guess Your Age and Edward Streeter's Father of the Bride. He has also done many drawings for magazines such as Cosmopolitan, Life, and the New Yorker, contributing to the latter his famous "Wedding Series". From 1922 to 1947, Williams drew daily newspaper cartoons that were published through the Bell Syndicate in various newspapers in the United States, England, Australia and other nations.
Williams is also the author of several books, including The Gluyas Williams Book, (1929); Fellow Citizens, (1940); and the Gluyas Williams Gallery, (1957).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Gluyas Williams Papers consist of biographical material, correspondence, manuscripts, drawings, and published material.
Correspondence consists of thirty-two letters of incoming correspondence; senders include Robert Benchley, Charles Dana Gibson, and Christopher Morley.
Manuscripts are all by other authors. There is a poem written by Kenneth Bird (Fougasse) about Gluyas Williams for the Christian Science Monitor and prefaces by Robert Benchley for two of Williams' books, Fellow Citizens (1940) and The Gluyas Williams Book (1929).
Drawings contains book illustrations, magazine cartoons and newspaper cartoons. Most of the book illustrations were done for various Robert Benchley titles but there are also illustrations for books by three other authors. Magazine cartoons appeared in Cosmopolitan, Life, and the New Yorker. The newspaper cartoons were published through the Bell Syndicate from 1922 to 1947 in various newspapers in the United States, England, Australia, and elsewhere.
Published material consists of two of Gluyas Williams' books, Fellow Citizens (1940) and The Gluyas Williams Book, (1929). Both copies are autographed. These items have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by sender. Book illustrations are arranged alphabetically by book title; magazine cartoons chronologically by magazine; daily newspaper cartoons, alphabetically by caption.
Related Material
has the collection of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
Two of Gluyas' books have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Art -- Illustrators; Adams, Randolph G.; Benchley, Robert, 1889-1945.; Benchley, Robert, 1889-1945. -- Fellow Citizens.; Benchley, Robert, 1889-1945. -- Gluyas Williams Book.; Bird, Kenneth.; Ford, Corey.; Freeman, William.; Gibson, Charles Dana, 1867-1944.; Lobrano, G. S.; Morley, Christopher, 1890-1957.; Nassau, D.; Ross, Harold Wallace, 1892-1951.; Streeter, Edward, 1891-; Sullivan, Frank.; White, K. S.; Williams, Gluyas, 1888-1982.; Cosmopolitan (New York, N.Y.: 1952); Life (New York, N.Y.); New Yorker (New York, N.Y.: 1925); American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Illustrators -- United States.; Book illustrations.; Cartoons (humorous images); Correspondence.; Manuscripts (document genre); Cartoonists.; Illustrators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Gluyas Williams.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - Adams, Randolph G., 1933 (Box 1)
    - Benchley, Robert, 1934; 1937 (Box 1)
    - Bird, Kenneth, ("Fougasse" of Punch), 1925; 1936,; 1944 (Box 1)
    - "Der Querschnitt", 1936 (Box 1)
    - Gibson, Charles Dana, 1918; 1921,; undated (Box 1)
    - Lobrano, G.S., undated (Box 1)
    - Morley, Christopher, 1929-1930; undated (Box 1)
    - Nassau, D., 1929 (Box 1)
    - Ross, H.W., 1929; 1934,; 1942,; 1943,; 1947,; 1948,; undated (Box 1)
    - Sullivan, Frank, 1949 (Box 1)
    - White, K.S., 1935 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Article about Gluyas Williams by Kenneth Bird ("Fougasse") for Christian Science Monitor (Box 1)
  - Preface to Fellow Citizens, by Robert Benchley, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Preface to The Gluyas Williams Book, by Robert Benchley, 1929 (Box 1)
- Drawings
  - Book illustrations
    - After 1903, What? by Robert Benchley, 1938; 4 items (Box 1)
    - Benchley Roundup by Robert Benchley, undated; 2 items (Box 1)
    - Chips Off the Old Benchley by Robert Benchley, undated; 11 items (Box 1)
    - Father of the Bride by Edward Streeter, undated; 30 items (Box 1)
    - From Bed to Worse by Robert Benchley, 1934; 7 items (Box 1)
    - Hear! Hear! by William Freeman, undated; 6 items (Box 1)
    - How to Guess Your Age by Corey Ford, 1950; 18 items (Box 1)
    - My Ten Years in a Quandary by Robert Benchley, 1932; 21 items (Box 1)
    - "No Poems" by Robert Benchley, 1932; 17 items (Box 1)
    - The Treasurer's Report by Robert Benchley, 1938; 4 items (Box 1)
  - Magazine cartoons
    - Cosmopolitan, 1928; 1929; 8 items (Oversize 1)
    - Life, circa 1926; 1927; 5 items (Oversize 1)
    - The New Yorker
      - "Industrial Crisis Series", 1928; 1929,; 1933,; undated; 7 items (Box 2)
      - "The Inner Man Series", 1940 (Box 2)
      - "Raconteurs Series", 1938; 1939,; undated; includes negative and print of one item; 15 items (Box 2)
      - "The Reading Public Series", 1942; 1943,; undated; 6 items (Box 2)
      - "The Visiting Public Series", undated (Box 2)
      - "The Wedding Series", June 5, 1948; includes negative and print of one item; 14 items (Box 2)
      - "The Wedding Series: Wedding Reception" (Oversize 1)
      - Williams' first drawing for The New Yorker, 1926 (Box 2)
      - "The Writing Public Series", 1945 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper cartoons, daily, by caption
    - B-N, 1922-1947; 18 items (Box 2)
    - P-W, 1922-1947; 18 items (Box 2)
    - Clipping, circa 1970; from London newspaper (Box 2)
- Published material
  - Fellow Citizens, autographed, 1940
    Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
  - The Gluyas Williams Book, autographed, 1929